dr. ir. Rein Houthooft

Happy Algorithm Inc. 2 Embarcadero Center San Francisco, CA 94111 USA

Phone: +1 (415) 254 5315

Nationality: Belgium (USA research/STEM O1 visa)

email: rein.houthooft@gmail.com URL: reinhouthooft.github.io

be.linkedin.com/in/reinhouthooft

Summary

Expertise in fundamental AI/ML research, specifically focusing on deep learning, with a strong publication track record. ML engineering and applied research management experience in building high-throughput online recommendation/personalization systems. See reinhouthooft.github.io for a more complete description.

Current position

Head of AI, Happy Algorithm Inc. en.happyelements.com/ai

Areas of specialization

Artificial Intelligence • Machine Learning • Software Engineering

Experience

2008-2012

2017-2018 2014-2017 2016 2012 2011	Research Scientist, OpenAI
	Education
2014-2017 2016 2012-2014	Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering

B.Sc. in Industrial Engineering Associatie KU Leuven, Belgium

Professional service

Reviewer, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)

Programm Comittee, NeurIPS Deep Reinforcement Learning Workshop

Grant Reviewer, Swiss National Science Foundation

Reviewer, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters

Reviewer, International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

Organizer, NeurIPS Deep Reinforcement Learning Workshop

Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence

Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing

Organizer, NIPS Deep Reinforcement Learning Symposium

Teacher, Deep Reinforcement Learning Bootcamp at UC Berkeley

Program Committee Member, NIPS Deep Reinforcement Learning Workshop

Reviewer, Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)

Publications

2018

2016

2018

2017

2016

CONFERENCE ARTICLES

Houthooft, R., Chen, R. Y., Isola, P., Stadie, B. C., Wolski, F., Ho, J., Abbeel, P. (2018). Evolved Policy Gradients. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, Montreal, Candada

Stadie, B. C., Yang, G., Houthooft, R., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Yuhuai, W., Abbeel, P., Sutskever, I. (2018). Some Considerations on Learning to Explore via Meta-Reinforcement Learning. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, Montreal, Candada

Plappert, M., Houthooft, R., Dhariwal, P., Sidor, S., Chen, R.Y., Chen, X., Asfour, Y., Abbeel, P., and Andrychowicz, M. (2018). Parameter Space Noise for Exploration. *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*.

Tang, H., Houthooft, R., Foote, D., Stooke, A., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Schulman, J., De Turck, F., and Abbeel, P. (2017). #Exploration: A study of count-based exploration for deep reinforcement learning. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)*, Long Beach, USA

Houthooft, R., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Schulman, J., De Turck, F., and Abbeel, P. (2016). VIME: Variational information maximizing exploration. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* (NIPS), pages 1109–1117, Barcelona, Spain.

Chen, X., Duan, Y., Houthooft, R., Schulman, J., Sutskever, I., and Abbeel, P. (2016). InfoGAN: Interpretable representation learning by information maximizing generative adversarial nets. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)*, pages 2172–2180, Barcelona, Spain.

Duan, Y., Chen, X., Houthooft, R., Schulman, J., and Abbeel, P. (2016). Benchmarking deep reinforcement learning for continuous control. In *Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, pages 1329–1338, New York, USA.

Houthooft, R., De Boom, C., Verstichel, S., Ongenae, F., and De Turck, F. (2016). Structured output prediction for semantic perception in autonomous vehicles. In *Proceedings of the 30th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence*, Phoenix, Arizona, USA.

Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2015). Robust geometric forest routing with tunable load balancing. In *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)*, pages 1382–1390, Hong Kong, P.R. China.

2014

2015

Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2014). Fault-tolerant greedy forest routing for complex networks. In *Proceedings of the 6th International Workshop on Reliable Networks Design and Modeling (RNDM)*, pages 1–8, Barcelona, Spain.

De Backere, F., Hanssens, B., Heynssens, R., Houthooft, R., Zuliani, A., Verstichel, S., Dhoedt, B., and De Turck, F. (2014). Design of a security mechanism for RESTful Web service communication through mobile clients. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS)*, pages 1–6, Krakow, Poland.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

2015

Houthooft, R. and De Turck, F. (2016). Integrated inference and learning of neural factors in structural support vector machines. *Pattern Recognition*, 59:292–301.

Houthooft, R., Ruyssinck, J., van der Herten, J., Stijven, S., Couckuyt, I., Gadeyne, B., Ongenae, F., Colpaert, K., Decruyenaere, J., Dhaene, T., and De Turck, F. (2015). Predictive modelling of survival and length of stay in critically ill patients using sequential organ failure scores. *Artificial Intelligence in Medicine*, 63(3):191 – 207.

Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2015). Optimizing robustness in geometric routing via embedding redundancy and regeneration. *Networks*, 66(4):320–334.

PATENT APPLICATIONS

Houthooft, R., Verstichel, S., Debilde, B., and Foster, C. A controller for a working vehicle. E.U. Patent Application No. 16177346.0 - 1905. U.S. Patent Application No. 15/199,090. Filed 30 June 2016.